This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
>> [music]
>> Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Bhrijesh Amaranth, and
today my guest is Rob Buafat. Rob is the
author of Risk-First Software
Development. Rob is an open-source
enthusiast, full-stack software
developer, and author working in
finance. Rob works on open-source
projects for FINOS, the Fintech Open
Source Software Foundation, as Chief
Technical Architect. Rob, welcome to the
show. Hi Bhrijesh, thanks for having me
on. It's good to talk to you. Excellent,
let's dive in. So, most developers think
they're in the business of writing or
shipping features or writing code. You
argue that they're actually in the
business of managing risk. Why is risk
the hidden engine behind every line of
code we write?
And why don't most developers realize
that? Yeah, essentially Bhrijesh, that
is the entire thesis of what I'm writing
about in Risk-First. So, I have a book
out called Risk-First Software
Development, and also a website,
riskfirst.org. And that is the essential
idea behind it, that actually software
development, and actually all kinds of
work really, are just an exercise in
risk management. But it does take a bit
of a change of perspective to be able to
start seeing software in that manner.
And so, really what I'm trying to do
throughout the book is to introduce that
perspective. And it can be hard work to
begin with, but let's take a simple
example, right? So, let's say you're
working on a piece of software, and
you're writing a feature for that
software. Maybe you're writing a search
feature or something like that. Now, the
reason you're writing this feature, the
reason in fact you're writing all the
features of your software, is to try and
make that software better for the users.
And that in essence, is managing a risk.
What you're doing there is you're
managing the risk that the users aren't
going to use your software, and
therefore your company's not going to
make money through that software, and
then maybe your company goes bust
because of that. Assuming that is you're
selling software, maybe like a SaaS or
some kind of commercial software. And
so, you can see there's a very
straightforward relationship there
between writing good features in the
software and managing the risks of the
business. This is the case across pretty
much everything that goes on in
software. To give another example, if
you're writing unit tests, what you're
trying to do really is to avoid
implementation risk in the software,
bugs creeping in. And again, that's
going to affect users down the line.
That might encourage people to move away
from your software and use something
else. Or might maybe if you're working
for a bank, like I've worked for many
banks, there could be serious
consequences of bugs making it into
production where money is moved to the
wrong people or ends up in the wrong
accounts or is counted up wrongly. And
so, these implementation risks turn out
to be whole operational risks for the
bank. And these are things that banks
like to measure and track. And so,
really the book is an exploration of
this whole idea about how actually,
although we enter this industry as
software developers wanting to write
code and wanting to be good about our
craft, there's this underlying balance
that's this risk landscape at play. And
all the time what you're doing is you're
working to minimize risks or moving to
positions on the risk landscape where
your software is in a more favorable
position with more favorable risk facing
it. So, that cover it? Yeah, it does.
But maybe expanding a bit more on that,
how does changing the focus to risk,
rather than features, help the project
or the product that you're developing?
Yeah, that's a really good question. So,
I think I'm going to assume that most of
your audience are really familiar with
traditional software development. Maybe
you you work in like a Scrum team or
with Kanban or some kind of lean
approach or DevOps. Now, those
approaches, sometimes they work,
sometimes they don't. Often they're
great and they work well. But what you
have to remember is that in all those
cases, you are actually just trying to
manage risk. So, if I'm using Scrum and
trying to limit my work to a couple of
weeks work or having reviews and
retrospectives, all these activities are
in the service of managing risk on the
project. For example, like work in
progress, having lots of work in
progress turns out to be risky. That
makes your life more complicated. It
means that features turn up later for
users and that leads into that feature
risk that I was talking about. So, I
guess the way to look at this is that
yes, all the techniques and tools that
we use in software development, they all
still apply. But what I'm trying to do
is suggest that the reasons why some
tools work better than others in certain
situations is because they turn out to
be better at managing risks. And so,
having that more holistic understanding
of what you're doing and the risks that
you face in your work will actually be
better off and help you choose the right
techniques.
So, if I understand that's right, what
you mean is that the current
methodologies like Scrum and Kanban,
they've been created to solve specific
problems. Like Scrum for visibility, you
have visibility for the next two weeks
if that's your sprint cycle. And if it's
Kanban, it's for flow to understand if
flow is getting impeded or it's getting
blocked by certain work items. And in
this context, where do they fall short
and how does the Risk-First framework
solve for it? And also, if you can help
me understand is the Risk-First entirely
new framework or does it work with the
existing frameworks like Scrum or
Kanban?
Or does it replace it? Okay, so that's a
really good question, really insightful
question. So, let's start What I want to
do is introduce the audience to the idea
of a risk framework. And a risk
framework generally, from working in
finance, we see lots of these. But, the
idea of a risk framework is that you
have a particular context or a
particular domain you're working in, and
you break down the risks in that domain,
and you enumerate what they are. And
then you have a number of techniques or
practices or tools or controls that
you're using to manage those risks.
And so, there's an interplay between
those things. There's the risks on the
one side, and then there's the
techniques and controls that you're
using on the other side. And so, if you
think about something like XP, for
example, XP recommends a number of
different practices like test-driven
development and pair programming. And
those are the things on the right-hand
side, they're the controls, if you like,
or the techniques. On the left-hand
side, the risks. If you read the
literature on XP, it doesn't really talk
so much about the risks. But, the risks
are still there. So, if I think about
something like test-driven development,
the idea of that is to reduce the number
of bugs in my code, and it's also to
make the code more malleable and easier
to change, because if I make a change,
then I run my tests again, and if the
tests all still pass, I know that it was
a successful change. So, that is
managing a couple of risks there. So,
the technique of test-driven development
is managing the risk of introducing
implementation risks as you're changing
code, but it's also managing a
complexity risk. It allows you to
refactor your code more easily, and
therefore keep a lid on complexity, cuz
obviously refactoring is one of the ways
in which we can reduce unnecessary
complexity. So, actually going back to
XP, so the Kent Beck who invented XP,
the very first sentence in his book XP
Explained is, "It's all about risk." And
so, he was very aware of the idea that
what he was doing with managing risk.
But rather than explain what all those
risks were, he sort of dove into just
explaining what his techniques were for
solving them. So it's like he was
showing you the answers to the problem
without showing you the questions. Which
is kind of a weird approach in
retrospect, but that's what everybody
does. People are always telling you what
their techniques are and telling you
what they're doing to solve a problem,
but a lot of the time they're not
explaining the context of the problem
and the things they're solving for. And
so to answer the other half of your
question is like, does this replace
anything? It's not really replacing
anything. What I'm trying to do is
backfill that part of the risk framework
that was missing in books like XP
explained, which is to say give people a
list of the risks on that left-hand side
of the risk framework ledger and say
that these are the things that you care
about when you're doing software
development. And yes, you can carry on
using your existing tools, but you need
to be using the correct tools to manage
the correct risks. I'm sure all our
listeners know, but XP is extreme
programming and that's one of the
frameworks or the methodologies in
addition to Scrum and Kanban that's used
in software development. So if I can
summarize or try to ensure that I've got
your answer right, what you're saying is
that the risk-first framework primarily
provides context for why you're
following certain practices for the
methodology that you're following. So it
is
providing that overall context for the
practices within extreme programming or
Scrum or Kanban so that developers know
those activities that they're
performing, what risk does it actually
reduce? Have I got that right? Yeah,
that's exactly it. As I said, I've
broken down like a taxonomy of different
risks that we face on software projects.
And then in the book I expand on these
and I explain what they are and give
examples of each and the tools that you
can use. On the website I actually go
into more detail and I talk about all
these different development
methodologies we discussed and I talk
about each of the practices and how they
relate to the risks and which risks
apply to which practices and stuff. So,
I'm really trying to create a rich
network of what works with what else.
But, yes, I think you've nailed it
there. Yeah. Maybe double-clicking on it
a bit more to understand if a team
decides to implement the risk-first
approach, what does that actual workflow
look like? Say they want to start
implementing it from Monday morning.
What would that look like? Can you walk
me through that? Yeah, so I think what
I've been trying to stress so far is
that I'm not trying to tell people a
completely new way of developing
software. I'm not saying throw out
Kanban, throw out Scrum. If they're
working for you, that's great. You carry
on using them. What I am trying to do is
to try and show the reasons why they are
working. So, if you're using Scrum, some
certain Scrum practices, then the reason
it's working is it's because it's is
dressing these risks. But, you're right
in the sense that what I am saying is
that if you're working on a project,
what you should do is pay attention to
the risks. You should be looking at the
context you're working in and try to
break down the sort of risks you're
facing in a project and looking at those
and paying attention to those and you
can start to think about you can weigh
off different risks against each other.
You can look at how one risk might be
more important or less important to the
success or the health of the project
than another. And in the book, I dive
into a lot of different techniques for
this. Most of these will be familiar.
One is, for example, looking at how you
might handle different time scales. So,
a risk that you face now might be
discounted less than a risk that you
face in the future. Or, if you have
risks of different sizes or shapes, they
might be handled differently. You can
use feedback loops in your work to
uncover new risks because a lot of risks
stay hidden. You have to think about the
risks you don't know. And then also
within teams as well, you might have
communication issues between different
teammates or across the projects. You
need to think about communication risks.
You also need to think about the wider
context as well. What context is the
project running in? Is the company
itself facing certain risks? Is the
country that the company is operating
in? How does that affect the context of
your project? So there are various
different ways of looking at this. And
interestingly, when you start to think
about like the backlog for example, if
you have a bunch of work on your
backlog, often it can be difficult to
prioritize things on the backlog, but
looking at those, if you reconsider the
items on your backlog and just consider
them as a list of different risks. Try
and figure out, well, what is the risk
that this backlog item represents? That
can usually offer an insight as to what
you should be doing next. And do you
have any example or does any story come
to mind where getting this perspective
about risk first helped a team
successfully or what difference did it
make in their progress to completing a
project or a sprint? So this is one of
the things that I like to include a lot
of both in the book and on the website.
So I as I said, I've broken down
software development into different
types of risks. So I'm going to go
through a few of these now. So one is
that I look at feature risks, the risks
that a feature is present or not
present. And feature risks often break
down into things like, do I have the
right features for the people that are
going to be using my software? Does the
market value the features that I'm
creating? Are these valuable enough to
be worth something and worth doing? And
implementation as well, am I
implementing these features well enough
that other people are going to be able
to use them. So that's kind of the
feature risk side of things. And then I
also consider dependency risks. So,
obviously when we're building software,
you conclude things like libraries, but
you also have dependencies on things
like the internet or certain
infrastructure being available. And so,
dependency risks break down into things
like funding, processes, staff, agency,
deadlines and schedules, things like
this, having enough time to do things.
And obviously library dependencies,
database dependencies, things like this.
There's also things like model risks
where you're talking to other people,
communication risks, complexity. Your
understanding of the world is like a
model. And so, it's important that if
you're making moves in the world and
you're doing things that your model
aligns with that. But just to dive in to
a specific example, right? So, one of
the things I talk about is reliability
risk. Now, as software developers, this
is something I think about quite a lot
when I'm choosing a dependency, say like
a library dependency. Is this going to
be a reliable choice for my project or
am I going to regret this a few months
down the line? But reliability risk
shows up everywhere. So, one of the
examples I pick up on the website is in
the 1970s, Ford created a car called the
Pinto. And they put the fuel tank of the
car just behind the rear axle of the
car, which created this massive
reliability risk because if the car got
hit from behind, which is kind of a
super common thing, the fuel tank might
get punctured and explode. And this
happened over and over again to Ford and
they faced huge damages and there were
injuries and deaths and public outrage.
And so, all of this was caused by a
reliability failure in their software.
So, you can see that as a particular
example of reliability risk. But we face
face this stuff all the time in software
development with components having odd
edge cases where they become unreliable
or people putting lines of code in code
bases and then forgetting about them and
it going wrong in production in some
kind of unusual way. So, these all
represent reliability risks within
software. Hopefully, that sketches out
roughly what I'm talking about here.
Yes, and it does transition us nicely
into the next section that I wanted to
cover, which was double click into some
of the risks that you call out on your
site as well as in the book. But, before
that, I just want us to go back to the
methodology itself and ask a few
questions around that. So, is there a
specific ceremony or a check-in that
keeps the team focused on risk reduction
rather than just focusing on the risk
when we adopt the risk-first framework?
How do people keep risk on the top of
their mind? So, I think probably by this
point it's come clear that I'm not
trying to force a new methodology down
people's throats. However, what I am
suggesting that they do is to observe
the fact that risk is going to be at the
heart of their project's success or
failure. So, it would seem sensible to
have like a regular session where you go
and review the state of either your
backlog or you go talk to customers or
you review your environment. There's a
hundred and one ways in which you can
close the loop on what you're doing. So,
every time you do something in the
world, really, you should be seeking to
check to find out if what you did
actually had the impact that you hoped
for. And this is all a risk reduction
strategy, isn't it? Because if you don't
close the loop on work you're doing and
test it, then this opens you up to all
sorts of hidden risks and things not
working out the way you wanted. Your
model, essentially, is going to be
underspecified compared to reality and
you're going to be out of sync with
what's really going on. So, to answer
your question again, I'm not proposing
that people have a specific ceremony
around this, but nevertheless, in the
book I do propose a number of different
processes and things that you can adopt.
Struggling to advance in the software
industry?
As an experienced professional ready to
lead, pull ahead of your competition
with the new software professional
certification from IEEE Computer
Society.
Your expertise [music]
certified by the most trusted
professional organization in computing.
Take the lead in your career. Sign up at
computer.org/certification
today.
>> [music]
>> From a backlog perspective, usually the
backlog is prioritized based on a
feature priority. Does that still
continue or is there a risk ranked
backlog
which needs to be considered when you
have a risk-first approach? So, I would
challenge what is the feature priority?
How do you arrive at the priority of the
feature? I guess that's usually the
product owner and the business saying
that this is what's driving the
business. Or if it's financial domain,
if it's bank, it's regulatory. And then
you have a conversation where
technology, business, ops together to
agree on that priority. Yeah, but I
think what I'm saying is that that
priority will be based on the
perceptions that those people have of
the risks that they see. So, maybe the
product owner has one view of what the
riskiest item on the backlog is and
he'll want to drive towards that.
Whereas somebody else reviewing the same
backlog might have a different view. And
so, they would prioritize things
differently. But, the priority I'm
suggesting is actually formed by risk
and that is the underlying metric that
they're going to be trying to rank
things on. I was going to give a quick
example there because I'm not sure
>> Yes, that would help. if that was very
clear. So, one of the things that I see
over and over again working in finance
is that this is not that long ago. So,
there was a development team and there's
also like the business team. The
business obviously in finance often is
trying to get some new business, they're
trying to win some customers or
something like this. Whereas the
developers, they're doing their best to
fulfill the needs of the business. But,
often, push will come to shove and the
business people will say, "We need this
out yesterday. We need this working
right now." And the developers will suck
their teeth and go, "Okay, all right,
come on. We'll just hack something in
for now and we'll set it up." Now,
obviously, hopefully, you have time
afterwards to set things right and keep
your architecture straight. But,
sometimes, this keeps on happening and
you end up with technical debt. Well, I
think we've all been in situations where
there's been lots of technical debt. And
the problem I see a lot of the time is
that the developers will then go to the
business and say, "Look, we've got all
this technical debt. We've got all these
crazy edge conditions that you've asked
us for over the last few months. We've
introduced them and the software's in a
bad state now." And the business people
will say, "Yeah, that's all great, but
we need to do X, Y, and Z now. You're
just going to have to suck it up." Now,
at this point, this is kind of a failure
of communications because
what the developers should be doing is
not saying, "Oh, we see technical debt.
We need to stop what we're doing and fix
it." What they should be doing to the
business is saying,
"There are risks here in continuing down
this path. We see complexity risk all
over this system. And if we continue to
operate it like this, this is going to
end up in an operational risk. And
either customers will be upset or
they'll be frustrated that something's
not worked or there's going to be some
massive crashes or there'll be some odd
calculations happening and it's going to
end up in a massive reputational risk
for the firm or we're going to end up
losing money and it'll be a financial
risk." You can extrapolate and try and
paint the picture in terms of risk. And
if you're communicating throughout an
organization, then actually explaining
your position in terms of risk is a
really powerful way of crossing
different organizational boundaries from
one part to another because you can
start to talk in terms of the language
of risk and then hopefully people will
understand that language. Whereas if you
just go in saying, "Oh, we got lots of
duplication of functions and technical
debt and the bill keeps failing." That's
not going to land in quite the same way
as painting the picture of why it is
important to address these problems.
Yeah, it does bring it to light. I have
a related question. So,
I worked in a department previously in
in a bank and the department was market
risk. And within market risk, the
primary function of the department was
to
do various calculations and come up with
a number and that number was value at
risk. In terms of if the market
conditions moved, this would be the
value that would be at risk for the firm
at that certain point of time. The
probability of that risk happening was
quantified. The challenge in software I
see is that we are able to explain the
risk, but we are not able to quantify
it. So, we are not able to put a number
saying that if you have a tech debt or
technology debt, which is say of 100
items, that is translating into a dollar
value of the risk that the firm is
carrying. We are not able to do that and
that is a challenge that business is not
been able to understand how does that
convert to a risk to the firm. Do you
see that from that perspective? And if
you don't, how does the risk first
framework address that? Does it allow
developers or the software team to
quantify the risk? Yeah, that's a great
question. So, I also worked in the
market risk team in one of my earlier
jobs as well. So, before I answer that
though, I just wanted to pick up on
another suggestion here. So, it's
interesting, isn't it, that we worked in
the market risk team. And the way banks
tend to work is that Well, in fact, the
way a lot of companies work is that they
will have an organizational structure
and the organizational structure of the
company is often broken down into
different risks. So, if you think of
like the chief finance officer is really
in charge of financial risk. And then
the chief operational officer is in
charge of operational risk. And then
when you break it down into the risk
department that we work with for, we
have the market risk team and the credit
risk team and the liquidity risk. So,
you can sort of see how this works, this
idea of a taxonomy of risk. That's
written large in the organizational
structure of most firms. So, yes. So,
that is essentially what I'm trying to
do with software development is to
create that same taxonomy so that we can
start thinking about it in the same way
and breaking it down. But yeah, let's
get on to the question you asked which
was like, well, so the great thing about
value at risk was that you have a dollar
number, which is the amount of money
you're likely to lose on a given day 99
days out of 100, less than that,
assuming it's like a 1% VAR figure.
Obviously, the problem with value risk
one of the problems with value risk is
that it led a lot of people into a false
sense of security about how likely that
was to be the case. And when financial
disasters happen, it wouldn't be just
one day in a 100 where you'd lose that
amount of money. It'd be like four or
five days on the trot where you'd lose
that amount of money. And so, suddenly
the idea of value at risk starts to look
a bit shaky. It's based on some slightly
faulty assumption Well, these are not
faulty assumptions. These assumptions
are very clear in the model. But if
you're basing what you do on just a
model and accepting those assumptions,
it's kind of a bit dangerous. And that
has led to a lot of problems in finance,
hasn't it? So, you have to be very
careful, I guess, is the point I'm
making. You have to be very careful with
adding a dollar value to risks. But
getting back to the nub of the problem,
right? What you're saying is that, okay,
I'm presented with my backlog. I've
decided that all these items on my
backlog represent risks. I can figure
out using the Risk First taxonomy or I
can use my own taxonomy but I've worked
out what kinds of risks they all are and
I've worked out which risks I care about
most in reducing. But then, okay, is it
important to assign a dollar value to
each of these? So,
what I would suggest is that often it's
not that important. What you really need
to be able to do is to weigh up two
risks in your hand and say I've got risk
A and risk B. Which one is worse? Which
one do I care about more? And often
times it's kind of obvious. You can say
to yourself, "Oh, this risk is huge. The
risk of me running out of money at the
end of the month is massive. I really
need to sort that out rather than
worrying about translating the website
into French so I capture the French
market or something like that." I don't
know. But yes, often times you can just
sort of weigh these things by eyeball
and say this one's bigger than this one.
So, the risk is kind of metric. You
don't have to be completely exact about
the values, but certainly ordering them
is is very beneficial.
Right. Let's now deep dive into some of
the specifics of the Risk First
framework. You've seen a lot of projects
in finance and in open source.
Do you have a story or can you paint me
a picture of a project where a risk was
ignored? What What were the early
warning signs that the team missed?
Absolutely. So, the example I'm thinking
of is we ended up working in quite a
large IT project in a financial services
firm, let's just say. And my team was
working on like a data access layer and
it was communicating with a number of
different other teams like
infrastructure via
their different layers. It was kind of a
microservices kind of approach. So, each
different team was running their own
different layers. And
it was a massive team. There was maybe
30 or 40 people working in the the
entire project and maybe seven or eight
people just in my team working on this
data access layer.
Taking data out of a database and then
handing it on to another team for use in
some calculations.
What was weird about it was that
after
really sort of straining and pushing
hard with with a seven people team to
try and make this work, eventually we
kind of just de-scoped the whole thing
and we decided to write a library that
could be used by any of the other teams.
We got rid of the entire idea of using
like a microservice and we just handed
them a library where they could just
call it and run it in their teams. And
this was kind of a rewrite. Me and one
other guy just decided to rewrite this
thing. So, from a team of maybe a seven
or eight people working for a whole year
and building a thing that didn't quite
work, we went to a team of two people
working for three months building a
thing that did work. And it was a
completely different design.
And I think sort of just to try and
bring this back to risk first, I think
what went wrong here was that
the project was started with a big
budget and lots of fanfare and the teams
were stocked up with people, but it
wasn't completely clear what everybody
should be doing and the the
communication lines were not great.
There were really just too many people
working on the different components.
Does this make sense?
Yes. So, I think you're calling out
communication risk, maybe complexity
risk. Yes. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, and a
bit of agency risk as well where you
have people who really need to be doing
something and so they find work for
themselves to do. And so, yeah, people
were building stuff that perhaps didn't
need to be built.
I really understood agency risk because
that's something that you see in large
complex organizations where managers or
developers act in their own interest
rather than the firms.
How does a
risk first view help expose someone who
is pushing for a feature or tool because
it reduces that personal risk, so they
might be doing it for their own
visibility or for their own career
progression. Even if it increases
technology risk, they still do it, and
we have seen that happen time and again
in large organizations. How does a
risk-first framework address this? So, I
think really what risk-first is doing is
like collecting butterflies. It's
finding examples of these things and
pinning them down and attaching names to
them along with all the other risks that
we face, all the ones we've discussed
today, and just giving you that palette
of different risks to talk about that
affect your projects. So, in essence,
what I'm doing is cataloging things that
you and I have probably seen hundreds of
times over, and just making sure it's
written down and in in this sort of
taxonomy view. So, I'm not really
suggesting anything particular about it.
There are a bunch of So, for example, on
the website, I talk about how agency
risk occurs, like you get goal
misalignments where the goals of the
client and the goals of the employee
don't line up or a lack of trans-
parency where people are just able to
operate without oversight. And then
there's conflicts of interest where
certain members of staff have goals that
are not aligned with the goal of the
project or the company itself. And so,
all of these things kind of roll up into
this idea of agency risk where, you
know, the idea of agency risk, the term
agency risk comes from the idea of
principal agent problem, which is where
if you have some money and you want to
invest it,
then often you'll find an agent to help
you with that, like a financial advisor.
But, the problem, of course, is how do
you trust that they're going to do a
good job of that? So, yes, I'm kind of
pointing these things out, but yes,
obviously every time you have these
risks, there are already ways people
have found of trying to correct for
them. So, I'm not suggesting anything
new or novel here. What I'm doing is
just explaining what people have done in
the past. And so, things like having a
contract can help with agency risk or
having review processes, monitoring, you
know, getting people to commit to
estimates, this kind of thing. These all
help with agency risk problems. But,
yeah, again, you've heard of all these,
right? These are all things that we've
all used in the past before. Even
something like time boxing work, you
know, having short iterative cycles
helps with the agency risk problem
because then you're checking work every
so often rather than letting it go on
and on and on without oversight. All
right. You're giving a terminology for
the risks that are pre-existing and that
we are all aware of or we have seen it
sometime in our career. So, that
developers who are new can understand
what are the risks that they should look
out for.
Yes, exactly. Yeah. And so, essentially,
so what I'm doing really is applying
this sort of discipline of risk
management to software development in
general. So, that idea we just discussed
of trying to figure out what the the
palette of risks are that you're facing
and then coming up with a set of
controls or practices around around
those risks. This is what risk
management is and this is what a risk
framework is. So, I talked about at the
beginning about having the risks on one
side of the ledger and then the
practices on the other. And so, yes, I'm
just applying that that discipline, that
idea to software development. And the
ledger itself, is that
a concept of risk first framework? That
is that an artifact which is maintained
when you adopt risk first framework? So,
how do you make these risks surface? How
do you log it? How do you once you have
identified it, what are the next steps?
Yeah, so I'm using the term ledger there
just to
just to add a bit of like so I don't say
the words risk framework repeatedly over
and over again in your podcast and get
people bored cuz otherwise it does get a
bit one note. But, yes, so that's a good
question though. The idea of where do we
store this stuff? Where do we keep it?
We've already talked about like the
backlog, the idea that the backlog is in
itself kind of like a list of all your
risks you're facing. People often have
like a dedicated risk register where
they're keeping a list of risks. So, on
various projects that I work on for
FINOS, which as you said earlier, we're
an open source software foundation,
we're part of the Linux Foundation, it
turns out that quite a few of our
projects are all about building risk
frameworks. And so, we often embody
these in like GitHub projects in just
either in markdown files or in like
little microsites that explain what's
going on. So, just to give one example,
we've we've been building like an AI
risk framework recently. So, if you're
working in a finance firm and you want
to deploy AI as part of a software
system in that firm, it's like, "Well,
okay, well, what are the risks of doing
that? What do I need to think about? You
know, what do I have to control for?"
We break down all those risks and then
we talk about all the controls that you
might introduce to to manage those
risks. To answer your question then, it
happens in various different ways. We we
see this happening in in a number of
different ways. In like big
organizations like the banks we've
worked for, they will actually have a a
department that it really in charge of
the risk taxonomy at some high level
that's keeping track of all the risks.
Usually, there's a chief risk officer
who kind of keeps a register of all
these different risks that the bank
runs. Oh, and then the other example I
was thinking of the other day, even
something like So, I I live in the UK,
the UK government has a risk register
where it keeps track of all the
different risks facing, you know, the UK
as a whole. And this is a document you
can actually download from the UK
government website and it has all sorts
of things like violent storms or like
economic collapse or like major fires or
all sorts of risks that they worry about
and they they sort of record them all in
the risk register and try and assign
like the impact cost and the likelihood
of of these risks happening. You've
written extensively about the
intersection of AI and risk. What are
the some of the biggest risks that you
see companies taking on right now when
they deploy AI to production? That's a
big topic, isn't it? The problem with
this topic topic is that it's incredibly
fast-moving. So, you know, the state of
the art is changing fairly constantly.
And what's being done now is probably
not what we'll be doing in a year's
time. So, that risk framework that I was
talking about, the AI risk framework
that Finos has written, it had its
second revision last summer. And even
then,
within about 3 months, we realized that
there was a whole load of stuff about
agentic AI that we hadn't included.
That's something that's, you know, with
all this open claw and everything else.
This is all really current. We're sort
of rushing to keep up with that in these
projects.
So, for example, on the operational
side, we have things like hallucination.
Right, we're all aware of the This
hallucination risk has got less, I
think, over the last year, but it's
still the case that you can get AI
systems to hallucinate, you know, crazy
stuff and give you the wrong answers.
And if we're back in the world of
finance, and there's some kind of
important financial system behind or,
you know, involved with this AI, that
could be a terrible cost right there.
There's a really interesting example of,
I think, I can't remember the name of
the airline company, but they had an AI
chatbot on their website. And somebody
managed to had a conversation with the
AI bot saying that a member of their
family had died. And so, were they
entitled to money back off the tickets
that they'd bought? And the bot was
like, yes, of course, you should
definitely have money back. And so,
person filled out the bots the bot the
forms the bot asked it to fill out. And
then the company declined the offer. And
so, then the person actually sued the
airline and won. Won damages because the
bot had said it was allowed to have the
money back. So, this is an example of
like a hallucination problem, where the
bot has hallucinated that the idea of
someone being allowed a compensation,
and then it actually coming to pass that
they got the compensation. So, this
stuff has real material impact. Things
like bias and discrimination, or lack of
explainability, and reputational risk,
we talk about that. So, that's another
good impact of the thing I've the
example I've just given. Information
being leaked. So, if you wire up your AI
system to sensitive information sources,
and then rely on the AI to be the
gatekeeper, it could be easily like
prompt injected to give out information
that it's not supposed to give out. So,
all of these risks are things we talk
about on the website. And yes, in the
book as well, I sort of dive into this
stuff. I like to What I've tried to do
at the at the end of the book is to try
and apply the risk first framework to
what we're seeing now, in terms of the
world of AI software development, AI and
the effect it's having on society as a
whole. And although I can't really, like
I haven't got a crystal ball, I can't
tell you exactly what's going to happen.
What I can tell you is that risk
management is really our best tool in
the box for managing through this change
that we're seeing in the world of moving
towards autonomous intelligent software
systems. This is really the best hope
that we have of doing this in a safe
way, and managing the the the downsides
that there are in AI.
Continuing with that, do you see any
specific risks emerging because of use
of agentic AI, where AI agents are
committing code to our repositories? And
do you see any new risks emerging
because of this?
Yeah, I am sort of fascinated in this
stuff at the moment. So, I'm trying to
put together a little risk framework
about exactly this. One of the biggest
ones that I kind of been worrying about
a lot recently is the idea that if
you're faced with some software that's
actually quite reliable. And we see this
in like self-driving cars. If you have a
system that works 99% of the time, then
what happens is a process called
vigilance minimization where people will
slowly over time just assume that the
system's going to work fine up until the
point where it doesn't. So and that
could quite easily apply to I'm not sure
you're using as much AI in your work as
I am now, but you know, if you're
assuming that the AI is going to do a
good job and it does 99% of the time,
then there are always then eventually
that's going to catch you out. And I
think this is something that I worry
about a lot these days. I I'm sort of
thinking how can we build systems where
we, you know, control for that. How do
we make a system where vigilance doesn't
get reduced over time?
I'd be interested to see what you think
about that. Yeah, like you said, it's a
fast-evolving world. And I think the
bank Well, at least the bank that I'm
working in has taken the approach that
everything's tightly governed around
here because we just can't put any of
our customer information or customers at
risk. Right. Yeah.
>> too fast.
But at the same time, you must be
worried that one of your competitors
will steal a march on you and then do
something amazing in the space and steal
business, I guess, right? That's the
flip side of that. Yes. Okay. Which is
why Yeah, you want to keep a close watch
and understand what's happening in that
domain and that area.
But move cautiously because
the risk of getting things wrong
far outweighs the risk of not being the
first to roll out a new feature or a new
product, I guess,
using AI. I think you're right. I I
think it will probably also depends on
the size of the organization and how
much they have to lose as well, don't
it? you're working for one of the big
tier one firms, that's much must be very
much the mindset. Whereas if you're
working for some small challenger bank,
maybe that's not going to be the case
and they're going to be thinking, we
need to aggressively push into this
technology and and try and do something
that's going to capture the public
imagination with it.
Yes. Does that mean the risks differ
based on
factors like the size and size of the
organization? Yeah, exactly. So, that's
a a really good point, isn't it? So,
going back to something like the AI
governance risk framework,
in order to build that, we collected
together people who worked across the
banking industry, worked for multiple
different firms, and they all sort of
collaborated on producing this list of
risks. The good thing about that is, and
this is something I mentioned in the
book as well, is that the more people
you have, the more different opinions
you have, the better collection of risks
you'll end up with. And that's kind of
the reason why all these firms wanted to
collaborate together, cuz they knew that
they'd end up with a better result than
if they any individual firm did it
themselves. But yes, you're absolutely
right. Um
although they can agree on what the
risks are, they're not going to agree on
how important those risks are, the the
size of the threat to them, you know?
So, different firms are going to have
different opinions about both the the
impact of that risk on them, but also
the probability of it happening. So, as
a software developer, you need to be
aware of the context because if you move
from a big organization to a fintech,
the importance you give to the same risk
will be quite different.
Yes. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Related to the
organization you're working in FinOps,
banks usually, you know, the chief
security officer in a bank is usually
takes an approach or takes a view that
we must control everything.
How does FINOS help to change that
perspective to we can collaborate
safely?
And how does the risk first framework
help support those conversations?
So, when you say the security office,
you mean like cybersecurity, I presume?
Yes. Yes.
>> Yeah. So, this is a really good
question. Within FINOS, I work on a
project called common cloud controls.
And as you can probably guess, common
cloud controls is a risk framework. So,
what we've done is we've taken all the
commonly used cloud services. So, things
like managed Kubernetes or object
storage or relational databases, and
we've broken them down into what they
do, and then we've broken them and we've
looked at the risks on those things. So,
we've tried to do a risk analysis of the
different services. And then we've
started working out what the controls
are that you need to run those services
safely in a financial services
organization. So, you think this is
another example within FINOS where risk
frameworks are useful. And there are a
bunch of others that we might get into.
So, your question really was like, why
would a bank or a financial services
firm, why would they want to use that
rather than come up with their own
internal approach to this? And there's a
couple of reasons. So, the first reason
is that maintaining like a this sort of
suite of cybersecurity controls is kind
of hard work. And it's also, if you can
think about it, there are people in
every different firm doing exactly the
same thing. So, all of the big financial
services firms in the city or your city
or my city are doing exactly that same
work. They're all building the same set
of controls. And to a greater or lesser
to extend, they're, you know, doing a
better or worse job of it. And so, this
is kind of like a basic argument for
open source, really, because what we're
saying is that stop building those
controls on your own, build them
together, and do a better job as a group
than you would otherwise do
individually. Now, proje- it turns out
that getting financial services firms to
engage in open source is very difficult,
and that's probably a whole other
podcast that we can get into. It's not
as simple as I've made it sound. If if
it was, we'd be done a long time ago.
But yes, the the idea is that if they
all come together and they collaborate
on these things as a group, they will
end up with something better than they
would if they were just doing it on
their own. And then also, the more
people that get involved in this, the
less work they have to do. It's sort of
just divide and conquer essentially. And
yeah, I think
that is the basic argument for any open
source. It's just a question of
persuading the right people in firms to
to allow it to happen, I think. And what
it tends to boil down to is that or what
it should boil down to is that where
people are working on some kind of
commodity work that is going to be
repeated in lots of organizations, they
should probably be doing that in an open
source project. And where they're doing
something that is generating alpha,
where it's unique to their firm, that's
where they should keep it in-house and
keep it as the secret sauce. But I don't
know about you, Bajesh, but I've over
the course of my career, I've been to
various different firms and done pretty
much the same job at a number of
different places. And I guess that's the
bread and butter for a lot of people
working in finance, and it's one of the
reasons why all the financial services
firms, you know, co-locate in the you
know, the city, the financial districts
in a city. It's so that the staff can
move from one firm to another. But open
source offers a much better way of
sharing this knowledge between between
firms than just having your staff moving
around, I think. So that's the
glittering prize of of like working on
something like common cloud controls.
Right. And I was just trying to overlay
the risks that the categories of risks
that you had mentioned earlier in terms
of, you know, if you looked at using
open source or building your own
software, what risk would be would we be
reducing if we used open risk and what
risk would increase if we used open risk
open source and similarly, if we built
our own software, custom one, what risks
would we be reducing and what would we
be increasing? Can you help me with
that?
And again, this is another side of the
the work I've been doing at FINOS is is
building a risk framework for exactly
that. So, try and catalog the different
risks of open source.
Before I go on there, there's kind of
two sides to open source. There's open
source consumption where you're pulling
in libraries and using them in your
organization. And then there's open
source contribution. And so, they're
kind of different things and they have
different risk profiles. And it's almost
the case that I don't really need to win
an argument about open source
consumption. Like every firm is using
open source left, right, and center.
There was some Red Hat's study recently
where they said that like something like
90-something percent of every single
piece of software is open source
components. Certainly all the software
I've built in my career has brought in
open source dependencies and it's run on
things like Linux and
what have you. So, using open source is
kind of a no-brainer. What they need to
do when they're using open source is
make sure they think about license
compliance or supply chain security or
inventorying their components. So,
that's one side of things and it's
surprising how often that goes wrong,
but those risks at least are well known.
So, on the contribution side, it's like,
what are the risks of contributing to
open source software and what are the
risks of not contributing to open source
software? So, that's the interesting
part. So, if you're not contributing to
open source software,
then perhaps you're not able to steer
the direction of the project. That's
kind of a big thing for something like
common cloud controls. If you're not
contributing to open source software,
then maybe you will not see the benefits
of talent arriving at your firm. Often,
having a good open source posture is
very attractive to developers arriving
at your organization. It's kind of like
a mark of the quality of the development
work going on in your firm. And one of
the big ones is that if you don't allow
staff to contribute to open source
software, and then they find an issue in
that software, an open source component
that they want to use, what they'll do
is they'll take a copy of that software,
they'll stick it in their internal
source control, and then they'll make
the change locally, and then they'll
support that from that day forwards
forever. That's both expensive, so it's
got financial risk associated with it.
That developer is now wasting a lot of
time integrating upstream dependencies,
but it's also a security risk because
the chances are they're not keeping that
branch up to date with what's going on
in the public repo, either. So, there's
a whole bunch of risks there if you
don't contribute to open source
software. But then there's also a whole
bunch of risks if you do. So, one of the
key ones that firms really worry about
in regulated industries like finance is
that some, you know, hapless developer
will accidentally share some private
client information in a GitHub
repository, or they'll paste it onto
Facebook or or whatever. And you usually
the firewall policies in an organization
will prevent access to these sites and
prevent people from you know, doing HTTP
post requests and things like this in
order to minimize that risk. So, there's
this huge worry around accidentally
posting code that you didn't want to
release, or PII data, or materially
sensitive information, company secrets,
secret keys, server details, all this
sort of stuff. You've got to be careful
with all that. And so, just opening the
floodgates and allowing any employee to
use their work computer to contribute to
open source is a huge risk. And so,
Finos actually provides tools like Git
Proxy, which is like a proxy that sits
between your staff computer and then
GitHub or GitLab and allows for a like a
four-eyed review to occur to anything
you want to push to the open source
project. So, I guess what I'm saying is
that you don't have to just accept these
risks as they are. You can actually use
tools to manage those risks and and make
that open source contribution option
much more acceptable from a risk profile
point of view. Does that make sense?
Yes, it does. Thanks. I think we've
covered a lot of ground over here. Yeah,
we've used the word risk about a million
times as well, haven't we? So.
You know, as we conclude, my final
question would be, what's the one thing
you hope listeners will walk away
thinking about after listening to this
show? I think the final thing that I
would like people to take away is kind
of the central thesis of the book that
all work is risk management. It doesn't
matter what it is, right? If you're a
farmer and you're selling crops, you're
you're like, this is managing the risk
that people go hungry and and have
nothing to eat. And if you're uh I don't
know, think of another example, but this
applies to any kind of work you're
doing. I once had a friend who's a
lawyer and I was explaining the concept
of the book to them and they were like,
oh yeah, no, law is all risk management
as well. So, I guess what I'm saying to
the listeners is maybe go away and think
about what you're doing and test this
theory. Is all the work you're doing
risk management? Can you view it through
a risk management lens? And does that
actually help you decide what to work on
better? For me, it certainly does. I
find I use this lens all the time for
deciding how best to proceed on
projects. Excellent. Rob, thank you for
coming on the show. It's been a real
pleasure. This is Brijesh Ammanath for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
[music]
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5. [music]
Thanks for listening.